{"tossups": [{"question": "During a conflict in this region, one commander was baited into aiding the Aedui and was promptly defeated at the battle of Gergovia. The Arverni\u2019s resistance in this region broke after an enemy used the tactics of circumvallation and contravallation at the siege of Alesia. This region was divided into Cisalpine and Transalpine sectors and was conquered by Julius Caesar in 50 BC. Vercingetorix ruled in, for ten points, what Roman province in modern-day France?", "answer": "<b> Gaul</b> (prompt on France before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A Loyola law study found 31 cases \u201cout of a billion\u201d where these laws would have applied. In July 2016, one of these laws in North Carolina was struck down because it was targeting African-Americans with \u201csurgical precision.\u201d For ten points, name these laws that aim to prevent fraudulent behavior at the voting booth.", "answer": "<b> voter ID</b> laws (accept descriptions of laws that require<b> voter</b>s to provide any type of personal <b>identification</b>; prompt on partial answers or descriptions) (3) This man blamed stray American searchlights for providing vision for his enemy\u2019s guns at Agua Prieta. This post-Madero head of the Divisi\u00b4on del Norte worked with Emiliano Zapata to overthrow Venustiano Carranza. George Patton was among the leaders of a force sent to capture this man following his cross-border raid on Columbus, New Mexico. \u201cBlackjack\u201d Pershing failed to kill, for ten points, what general of the Mexican revolution? ANSWER: Francisco \u201cPancho\u201d<b> Villa</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An author from this country described spending seventeen months in a waiting line outside her son\u2019s prison in her poem<em> Requiem</em>. Parasha dies during a flood in this country, causing the man who loved her to descend into madness in a poem named after an equestrian statue. For ten points, name this setting of\u201cThe Bronze Horseman,\u201d the home country of poet Anna Akhmatova and the author of the verse novel <em>Eugene Onegin</em>, Alexander Pushkin.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b> (accept<b> Soviet Union</b> or<b> USSR</b> or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>; accept <b>CCCP</b> or <b>Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "The downtown of one city in this state was flooded in 1913 by the Great Miami River. A 1995 accord reached in this state ended the war in Bosnia-Herzegovina. Another river in this state caught fire several times, most famously in 1969. The northeastern portion of this state, once claimed by Connecticut as the Western Reserve, is home to the Cuyahoga River. For ten points, name this midwestern state, home to Dayton, Columbus, and Cleveland.", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This figure\u2019s body was found in the Tallahatchie River, weighed down by a heavy fan.<em> Jet</em> published images of this figure\u2019s funeral, at which his mother insisted on an open casket. After an all-white jury acquitted J.W. Milam and Roy Bryant of murdering this figure, they freely admitted their guilt in an interview with<em> Look</em> magazine. For ten points, name this 14-year-old from Chicago who was murdered in Mississippi in 1955.", "answer": "Emmett<b> Till</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Kuttabul</em> was sunk in a harbor in this country by three raiding midget submarines. A commander of this country\u2019s forces, Selwyn Porter, oversaw a series of defensive retreats in the Kokoda Track campaign. During World War II, this country was led by John Curtin and Robert Menzies. The Battle of Coral Sea effectively ended Japanese plans to isolate and invade this country. For ten points, name this Allied country that endured assaults on its harbors of Darwin and Sydney.", "answer": "<b> Australia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Four children of the More family were boarded onto this ship after their mother was embroiled in an adultery scandal involving Jakob Blakeway. Christopher Jones was the captain of this ship, which was originally intended to be accompanied on an ocean crossing by the<em> Speedwell</em>. The journals of William Bradford preserve a governing document or compact named for this ship. For ten points, name this ship that established the Plymouth Colony after landing at Cape Cod.", "answer": "<b> Mayflower</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This kingdom\u2019s first ruler was recognized by the papal bull<em> Manifestis Probatum</em>. This country is part of the oldest alliance still in effect, as it allied with England in 1373. A noble from this country created a school in Sagres and was head of the Order of Christ. It was ruled by the House of Braganza, and Henry the Navigator was part of its House of Aviz. For ten points, name this country that sponsored the first expeditions to India, which brought spices to its capital of Lisbon.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An expedition to this country ended in failure after the Battle of Verti\u00b4eres [vair-tee-air] and thousands of deaths to yellow fever. A civil war in this country called the War of the Knives ended with the exile of Andr\u00b4e Rigaud. This country\u2019s constitution declared its Governor-General for Life to be its revolutionary leader Toussaint L\u2019Ouverture. For ten points, name this French colony, the site of the only slave rebellion to successfully create a free state, found on the island of Hispaniola.", "answer": "<b> Haiti</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Lawrence Alma-Tadema painted a creator of this building showing its friezes to his friends. Entasis is used to give the appearance of straightness to this building\u2019s Doric columns. Reliefs of centaurs fighting the Lapiths were among the sculptures removed from this building by the Earl of Elgin in the 19th century. The Delian League\u2019s treasury was sacked to pay for the construction of, for ten points, what temple on the Athenian acropolis?", "answer": "The<b> Parthenon</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The acceptance of these legal items is governed by the \u201cmailbox\u201d rule. Severability clauses influence how eager courts are to amend these documents. A promissory estoppel may be granted by a court to remedy instances when these legal documents are violated. The \u201cright to [these]\u201d was enshrined by the Supreme Court during the Lochner Era. These documents typically consist of an offer, acceptance, intention, and consideration. For ten points, name these legal documents which establish legal duties between private individuals.", "answer": "<b> contract</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In response to this event, laywer Ludovic Trarieux [trair-you] created the Human Rights League. A bordereau central to this event was addressed to Max von Schwartzkoppen, the German military attach\u00b4e, promising state secrets. After the acquittal of this scandal\u2019s real culprit, Ferdinand Esterhazy, Emile Zola attacked Felix Faure\u2019s government with the open letter<em> J\u2019accuse</em>. For ten points, name this scandal in which the French government wrongly imprisoned a Jewish artillery officer.", "answer": "<b> Dreyfus</b> Affair (accept equivalents for affair, like scandal)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The largest city in this region hosts a yearly ice sculpture festival and was once home to the Jurchens. The \u201couter\u201d portion of this region, beyond the Amur and Ussuri Rivers, was ceded to Russia in a pair of Unequal Treaties. Harbin is the largest city of this region, where the Mukden Incident was used by Japan to establish the puppet state of Manchukuo. The Qing Dynasty was founded by people from, for ten points, what region in the northeast of China?", "answer": "<b> Manchuria</b> (accept<b> Manchukuo</b> after \u201cMukden\u201d is said and before it itself is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This battle took place near Horns Reef thanks to Room 40\u2019s success in decoding enemy messages. In this battle, several ships were destroyed during the Run to the South before a reversal and a Run to the North. In this battle, David Beatty\u2019s battlecruisers took heavy losses and were forced to withdraw until John (+) Jellicoe\u2019s main fleet arrived. This battle occurred despite the fleet-in-being strategy of the German High Seas Fleet, which tried to avoid action against the superior (*) </b> British Grand Fleet. For ten points, name this major 1916 battle, the largest naval battle of World War I.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Jutland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The X-15 research aircraft used liquid oxygen and this substance as rocket propellant.</b> <b>The Ostwald process converts this compound into nitric acid. In (+)</b> <b>1909, a method of</b> <b>producing this substance using an osmium or iron catalyst and components from the air was developed by (*)</b> Haber and Bosch, providing saltpeter-starved Germany with explosive material during World War I. For ten points, name this gas with chemical formula NH3, important in cleaning supplies and fertilizer.", "answer": "(anhydrous)<b> ammonia</b> (accept<b> NH</b><u>3</u> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b>AP reporter Robert Geiger first coined this term after witnessing Black Sunday. The SCS was created by Harold Ickes to deal with the aftermath of this event. A shelterbelt of</b> <b>over 200 million (+)</b> <b>trees was planted by the CCC in the wake of this event. Dorothea</b> <b>Lange\u2019s \u201cMigrant Mother\u201d shows one of millions of displaced (*)</b> \u201cOkies\u201d fleeing to California for work during this event. For ten points, name this widespread agricultural disaster that plagued the Great Plains during the Great Depression.", "answer": "<b> Dust Bowl</b> (do not prompt on Great Depression)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man wrote that he had once visited the \u201cthird heaven\u201d and seen \u201cthings man is not permitted to tell.\u201d Though he longed to travel to Bithynia, a vision inspired a visit</b> <b>to Macedonia instead. This man, who miraculously survived a (+)</b> <b>snakebite in Malta</b> <b>following a shipwreck, approved of the martyrdom of Stephen before falling to the ground and becoming blind in a (*) </b> conversion experience on the road to Damascus. For ten points, name this early Christian apostle and author of much of the New Testament.", "answer": "<b> Paul</b> (or<b> Saul</b> of Tarsus) Page 9", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>The theme of this piece\u2019s final movement was used for its composer\u2019s Opus 35 Variations and Fugue. In its first movement, a solo horn enters with the recapitulation four measures early. On the day of JFK\u2019s assassination, the Boston Symphony Orchestra altered its program to play this piece\u2019s second movement, a (+) funeral march. Its composer dedicated it \u201cto the memory of a great man,\u201d supposedly ripping up the original title page after (*) </b>Napoleon declared himself Emperor. For ten points, name this symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven.", "answer": "<b> Beethoven\u2019s Symphony</b> No.<b> 3</b> in E-flat major (or the<b> Eroica</b> Symphony; \u201csymphony\u201d and\u201cBeethoven\u201d are not needed after they are said)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This region was conquered after the Battle of Chuvash Cape and the defeat of Kuchum Khan. Tyumen was the first European settlement in this region. The Stroganov family financed the conquest of this region by a group led by (+) Yermak, leading to an explosion in the fur trade. This region\u2019s culture was driven by participants in the failed Decembrist revolt, who were (*) </b> sent here. The port of Vladivostok was selected as the eastern terminus of a railroad that crosses, for ten points, what enormous, desolate eastern region of Russia?", "answer": "<b> Siberia</b> (prompt on Russia)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s treasury secretary, Benjamin Bristow, exposed widescale bribery involving taxes on alcohol. This President was manipulated by James Fisk and Jay Gould in the (+)\u201cBlack Friday\u201d scheme to corner the gold market. During this man\u2019s re-election campaign against Horace Greeley, his opponents railed against his vice president, Schulyer Colfax, and others for taking bribes from a (*) </b> railroad construction company. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose administration was plagued by the Whiskey Ring and Credit Mobilier [moh-beel-yay] scandals, but whose reputation as a Union general earned him re-election.", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b>  (1) <b>In 1959, a leader of this country survived a plane crash and signed the London</b> <b>Agreements in the hospital. A military junta in this country hanged that man, Prime</b> <b>Minister Adnan Menderes, in 1960. The (+)</b> <b>PKK has fought with this country in</b> <b>an attempt to create an independent Kurdish state. This country defined its borders</b> <b>at the Treaty of Lausanne after rejecting the earlier Treaty of S\u00b4evres. This country</b> <b>is based on the (*)</b> \u201cSix Arrows\u201d philosophy of its founder, Mustafa Kemal Atat\u00a8urk. For ten points, name this nation governed from Istanbul. ANSWER:<b> Turkey</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}